Bernarda Bryson Shahn
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Bernarda Bryson Shahn papers
1872-2004, bulk 1904-2004
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Bryson, Bernarda Shahn
11.9 linear feet
The papers of painter, printmaker, and illustrator Bernarda Bryson Shahn measure 11.9 linear feet and date from 1872 to 2004, with the bulk of the materials dating from 1904-2004. Found within the papers are family and biographical materials, correspondence, writings including sound recordings of lectures by the Shahns, voluminous notebooks, five diaries, exhibition files, personal business records, printed material, seven scrapbooks, one sketchbook and other art work, and photographs. Although the bulk of the collection documents Bernarda's work, there are materials about or created by Ben Shahn scattered throughout the collection.
Provenance
The Bernarda Bryson Shahn papers were donated by the artist in 1983 and by her son Jonathan Shahn in 2005.
Related Material
Also found in the Archives of American Art are two oral histories with Bernarda Bryson Shahn, one completed in 1983 by Liza Kirwin and another in 1995 by Pamela Meecham. The Archives also holds the Ben Shahn papers.
Restrictions on Access
Use of original papers requires an appointment. Use of archival audiovisual recordings with no duplicate access copy requires advance notice.
Biographical Note
Bernarda Bryson Shahn (1903-2004) worked primarily in New Jersey as a painter, printmaker, and illustrator. She was married to Ben Shahn and often collaborated with him.
Bernarda Bryson was born on March 7, 1903 in Athens, Ohio, the daughter of the owner-editor of newspaper The Athens Morning Journal. After receiving early drawing and painting lessons from her mother, Bryson attended a private girls' school where she continued her studies in art and art history.
At Ohio University, Bryson majored in philosophy and attended art classes in which David Smith was a classmate. She later attended the Cleveland Art School where she studied printmaking.
Following graduation, Bryson taught etching and lithography at the art school of the Columbus Gallery of Fine Art. She also wrote for The Ohio State Journal and became editor of community paper The South Side Advocate. While in New York City to interview Diego Rivera, she met Ben Shahn who was assisting Rivera in painting the mural at Rockefeller Center. Bernarda Bryson and Ben Shahn were married in 1935.
Bernarda Bryson Shahn moved to New York and helped organize the Artists' Union and exhibited at the Whitney Gallery on Eighth Street. She then went to Woodstock to study lithography with Bolton Brown and was invited to set up a lithographic shop for the Resettlement Administration in Washington, D.C.
During the 1950s and 1960s, Bernarda Bryson Shahn executed illustrations for Harper's Magazine, Scientific American and Fortune in addition to random assignments from Life, Sports Illustrated and other publications. She illustrated many books including Wuthering Heights and Pride and Prejudice as well as writing and illustrating her own books Gilgamesh, The Twenty Miracles of Saint Nicolas, and The Zoo of Zeus. Following the death of her husband in 1969, she wrote and designed a large monograph Ben Shahn, published by Abrams.
In the mid-1970s, Bernarda Bryson Shahn won further recognition when she returned to painting.
Bernarda Bryson Shahn died on December 12, 2004 in Roosevelt, New Jersey.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of painter, printmaker, and illustrator Bernarda Bryson Shahn measure 11.9 linear feet and date from 1872 to 2004, with the bulk of the materials dating from 1904-2004. Found within the papers are family and biographical materials, correspondence, writings including sound recordings of lectures by the Shahns, voluminous notebooks, five diaries, exhibition files, personal business records, printed material, seven scrapbooks, one sketchbook and other art work, and photographs. Although the bulk of the collection documents Bernarda's work, there are materials about or created by Ben Shahn scattered throughout the collection.
Biographical material includes biographical accounts for Bernarda and Ben Shahn, identification cards, membership cards, awards, appointment books and calendars, address books, and a Japanese videotape about Ben Shahn.
Correspondence is primarily between Bernarda Bryson Shahn and publishers, educational institutions, and colleagues and friends including Leo Lionni, Russell Lynes, Robert Osborn, and Warren Robbins.
There are four linear feet of notes, notebooks, typescripts, and other writings by Bernarda Bryson Shahn and others, many of which concern Ben Shahn. Included are numerous files of research notes for published and planned books about Ben Shahn, notebooks concerning art-related topics, card files of art work, lists, sound recordings of lectures by the Shahns and Gwen Knight, and many typescripts of writings about art and Ben Shahn, among other topics. There is also a folder of notes by Ben Shahn for the Mural for the Rural Rehabilitation Program. Five of Bernarda Shahn's diaries contain very brief daily entries and some illustrations. The 1972 diary contains much more elaborate illustrations.
The exhibition files contain letters, notes, and printed material concerning exhibitions of art work by Ben Shahn.
Personal business records include files concerning property, the Skowhegan School of Painting and Sculpture, miscellaneous contracts, files concerning publishing, art price lists, and other scattered legal and/or financial records.
Printed material includes clippings, exhibition announcements and catalogs, press releases for Bernarda Bryson Shahn, Ben Shahn, and others, books including A Partridge in a Pear Tree, illustrated by Ben Shahn, and printed reproductions of art work. Seven scrapbooks also contain printed materials, notes, and photographs. Scrapbooks 1-4 document the creation of the Franklin Delano Roosevelt Memorial for which Jonathan Shahn created the large portrait bust. Scrapbooks 5-7 concern a book by Bernarda Bryson Shahn, and scrapbook 8 contains obituaries for Ben Shahn.
Art work includes a sketchbook with annotations, drawings, a portfolio of drawings, lettering designs, watercolor sketches, and layouts for publications.
Photographs are of unidentified and identified Shahn family members, Ben Shahn, Ben Shahn with friends and colleagues including Alexander Calder, Helen Hayes, Senator Jacob Javitz, and Nelson Rockefeller, Ben Shahn's studio, exhibition installations, and art work by Bernarda Bryson Shahn, Ben Shahn, and others. There are also travel photographs.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged as 10 series:
Series 1: Biographical Material, 1937-1999 (Box 1, 13; 35 folders)
Series 2: Correspondence, 1934-2004 (Box 1-5, 13, OV 14; 3.6 linear feet)
Series 3: Notes and Writings, 1946-2001 (Box 5-9; 4.0 linear feet)
Series 4: Diaries, 1965-1985 (Box 9; 5 folders)
Series 5: Exhibition Files, 1955-2000 (Box 9; 5 folders)
Series 6: Personal Business Records, 1932-2001 (Box 9, 10; 0.8 linear feet)
Series 7: Printed Material, 1904-2004 (Box 10-11, 13, OV 14-15; 1.2 linear feet)
Series 8: Scrapbooks, 1945-1978 (Box 11, 13, OV 15; 30 folders)
Series 9: Art Work, 1970-2002 (Box 11-13, OV 14; 70 folders)
Series 10: Photographs, 1872-1985 (Box 12; 34 folders)
Names and Subject Terms
This collection is indexed in the online catalog of the Archives of American Art under the following terms:
Subjects:
Calder, Alexander, 1898-1976--Photographs; Hayes, Helen, 1900-1993; Javitz, Jacob; Rockefeller, Nelson A. (Nelson Aldrich), 1908-1979; Shahn, Ben, 1898-1969
Subjects-Topical:
Illustrators--New Jersey--Roosevelt; Painters--New Jersey--Roosevelt; Printmakers--New Jersey--Roosevelt; Women artists--New Jersey--Roosevelt; Women painters--New Jersey--Roosevelt
Types of Materials:
Diaries; Drawings; Photographs; Scrapbooks; Sketches; Sketchbooks; Sound recordings; Watercolors
Names:
Knight, Gwendolyn; Lionni, Leo, 1910-; Lynes, Russell, 1910-1991; Osborn, Robert Chesley, 1904-; Robbins, Warren M.; Shahn, Ben, 1898-1969; Shahn, Jonathan, 1938-
Series Descriptions/Container Listing
- Biographical Material, 1937-1999, Series 1:; (Box 1, 13; 35 folders)
  Biographical Material includes a family history by Bernarda Bryson Shahn's aunt, biographical accounts for Ben and Bernarda Bryson Shahn, a passport and visa, membership cards and certificates, award certificates, appointment books and calendars containing brief entries, address books, and a Japanese videotape about Ben Shahn.
  - Family History by Stella Bryson Collins, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Family Stories by Bernarda Shahn, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Biographical Accounts for the Whitney Museum, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Miscellaneous Biographical Accounts, 1967-1993, undated, (6 folders) (Box 1, Folder 4-9)
  - Biographical Material for Ben Shahn, 1945-1967, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Passport and Visa for Bernarda Bryson Shahn, 1958-1980 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Library of Congress Card, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Membership Cards and Certificates, 1959-1994, undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Automobile Registration, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Award Certificates, 1956-1996, undated, (Oversized Material Housed in Box 13) (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Appointment Books and Calendars, 1958-1998, (8 folders) (Box 1, Folder 16-23)
  - Address Books, 1955-1956, undated, (6 folders) (Box 1, Folder 24-29)
  - Card File of Addresses, undated, (5 folders) (Box 1, Folder 30-34)
  - Japanese Videotape About Ben Shahn, undated (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Two Oversized Award Certificates, 1956-1989, (from Box 1, Folder 15) (Box 13, Folder 1)
- Correspondence, 1934-2004, Series 2:; (Box 1-5, 13, OV 14; 3.6 linear feet)
  Correspondence is primarily between Bernarda Bryson Shahn and publishers including Harry N. Abrams, Inc., Holt, Rinehart and Winston, Inc., and Macmillan and Company, and educational institutions including the Fogg Museum and Ohio University. Correspondence is also between colleagues and friends including Leo Lionni, Russell Lynes, Robert Osborn, and Warren Robbins. There are one or two letters each from Alexander Calder, Buckminster Fuller, Robert Indiana, and Archibald MacLeish.
  - Unidentified Correspondents, undated (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Correspondents with Unknown Surnames, undated, (11 folders) (Box 1, Folder 37-47)
  - Correspondents with Surnames "A," undated, (2 folders) (Box 1, Folder 48-49)
  - Correspondents with Surnames "B," undated, (2 folders) (Box 1, Folder 50-51)
  - Correspondents with Surnames "C," undated, (2 folders) (Box 1, Folder 52-53)
  - Correspondents with Surnames "D" - "E," undated (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - Correspondents with Surnames "F," undated (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - Correspondents with Surnames "G," undated (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - Correspondents with Surnames "H" - "I," undated, (2 folders) (Box 1, Folder 57-58)
  - Correspondents with Surnames "J" - "K," undated (Box 1, Folder 59)
  - Correspondents with Surnames "L," undated (Box 1, Folder 60)
  - Correspondents with Surnames "M," undated, (Oversized Material Housed in Box 13) (Box 1, Folder 61)
  - Correspondents with Surnames "N" - "O," undated, (3 folders; Oversized Material Housed in OV 14) (Box 1, Folder 62-64)
  - Correspondents with Surnames "P," undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Correspondents with Surnames "R," undated, (2 folders) (Box 2, Folder 2-3)
  - Correspondents with Surnames "S," undated, (8 folders) (Box 2, Folder 4-11)
  - Correspondents with Surnames "T," undated (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Correspondents with Surnames "V" - "Y," undated (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence, 1934-1943 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence, 1944-1945 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence, 1946 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence, 1947 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Correspondence, 1948, (2 folders) (Box 2, Folder 18-19)
  - Correspondence, 1949 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Correspondence, 1950 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Correspondence, 1951, (2 folders) (Box 2, Folder 22-23)
  - Correspondence, 1952-1953 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Correspondence, 1954 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Correspondence, 1955, (2 folders) (Box 2, Folder 26-27)
  - Correspondence, 1956, (2 folders) (Box 2, Folder 28-29)
  - Correspondence, 1957, (2 folders) (Box 2, Folder 30-31)
  - Correspondence, 1958 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Correspondence, 1959 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Correspondence, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Correspondence, 1961, (2 folders) (Box 2, Folder 35-36)
  - Correspondence, 1962, (2 folders) (Box 2, Folder 37-38)
  - Correspondence, 1963, (3 folders) (Box 2, Folder 39-41)
  - Correspondence, 1964, (2 folders) (Box 2, Folder 42-43)
  - Correspondence, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - Correspondence, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - Correspondence, 1967, (4 folders) (Box 2, Folder 46-49)
  - Correspondence, 1968, (7 folders) (Box 2, Folder 5-56)
  - Correspondence, 1969, (9 folders) (Box 2, Folder 57-65)
  - Correspondence, 1970, (6 folders) (Box 2, Folder 66-71)
  - Correspondence, 1971, (6 folders) (Box 2, Folder 72-77)
  - Correspondence, 1972, (7 folders) (Box 2, Folder 78-84)
  - Correspondence, 1973, (8 folders) (Box 2, Folder 85-92)
  - Correspondence, 1974, (4 folders) (Box 3, Folder 1-4)
  - Correspondence, 1975, (6 folders) (Box 3, Folder 5-10)
  - Correspondence, 1976, (6 folders) (Box 3, Folder 11-16)
  - Correspondence, 1977, (7 folders) (Box 3, Folder 17-23)
  - Correspondence, 1978, (6 folders) (Box 3, Folder 24-29)
  - Correspondence, 1979, (5 folders) (Box 3, Folder 30-34)
  - Correspondence, 1980, (4 folders) (Box 3, Folder 35-38)
  - Correspondence, 1981, (4 folders) (Box 3, Folder 39-42)
  - Correspondence, 1982, (5 folders) (Box 3, Folder 43-47)
  - Correspondence, 1983, (5 folders) (Box 3, Folder 48-52)
  - Correspondence, 1984, (4 folders) (Box 3, Folder 53-56)
  - Correspondence, 1985, (4 folders) (Box 3, Folder 57-60)
  - Correspondence, 1986, (5 folders) (Box 3, Folder 61-65)
  - Correspondence, 1987, (4 folders) (Box 3, Folder 66-69)
  - Correspondence, 1988, (5 folders) (Box 3, Folder 70-74)
  - Correspondence, 1989, (5 folders) (Box 3, Folder 75-79)
  - Correspondence, 1990, (3 folders) (Box 3, Folder 80-82)
  - Correspondence, 1990, (4 folders) (Box 4, Folder 1-4)
  - Correspondence, 1991, (8 folders) (Box 4, Folder 5-12)
  - Correspondence, 1992, (10 folders) (Box 4, Folder 13-22)
  - Correspondence, 1993, (11 folders) (Box 4, Folder 23-33)
  - Correspondence, 1994, (12 folders) (Box 4, Folder 34-45)
  - Correspondence, 1995, (10 folders) (Box 4, Folder 46-55)
  - Correspondence, 1996, (8 folders) (Box 4, Folder 56-63)
  - Correspondence, 1997, (3 folders) (Box 4, Folder 64-66)
  - Correspondence, 1998, (3 folders) (Box 4, Folder 67-69)
  - Correspondence, 1999, (4 folders) (Box 5, Folder 1-4)
  - Correspondence, 2000, (2 folders) (Box 5, Folder 5-6)
  - Correspondence, 2001 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, 2002-2003 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, 2004 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - An Oversized Illustrated Letter on Cloth from Joe Mason, undated, (from Box 1, Folder 61) (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Four Oversized Letters from Robert Osborn, undated, (from Box 1, Folder 64) (Box OV 14)
- Notes and Writings, 1946-2001, Series 3:; (Box 5-9; 4.0 linear feet)
  Notes and writings consist of miscellaneous notebooks concerning art-related topics, card files of art work and philosophical terms, address lists, miscellaneous lists, lectures by the Shahns and Gwen Knight recorded on compact discs, miscellaneous notes about art work and for publications, and typescripts for essays and books by Bernarda Bryson Shahn and others.
  - Notebooks, undated, (14 folders) (Box 5, Folder 10-23)
  - Notebooks Concerning Images of Satan, 1951, undated, (6 folders) (Box 5, Folder 24-29)
  - Notebook, 1956-1964 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Notebook, 1966 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Notebook, 1970 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Notebook, 1981 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Notebook, 1984 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Notebook "Dates of Painting and Other Things," 1985 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Notebook, 1987 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Notebook, 1993 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Notebooks Concerning Devils and Monsters, 1994, (2 folders) (Box 6, Folder 9-10)
  - Notebook, 1996 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Notebook "Reference: Bernarda Bryson Shahn's Published Material," 2005, (5 folders) (Box 6, Folder 12-16)
  - Card File of Art Work, undated (Box 6, Folder 17)
  - Card File of Philosophical Terms, undated (Box 6, Folder 18)
  - Address Lists, undated, (3 folders) (Box 6, Folder 19-21)
  - Miscellaneous Addresses, undated (Box 6, Folder 22)
  - Lists of Items Judged for University Women's Organization in Tokyo, Japan, undated (Box 6, Folder 23)
  - "Howard Greenfield Material," undated (Box 6, Folder 24)
  - List of Captions, undated (Box 6, Folder 25)
  - Lists of Names of People, undated (Box 6, Folder 26)
  - Compact Discs of Lectures by Ben Shahn, Bernarda Bryson Shahn, and Gwen Knight, 1954-1997, undated, (3 folders) (Box 6, Folder 27-29)
  - Notes for Book on Ben Shahn, 1956-1971, undated, (3 folders) (Box 6, Folder 30-32)
  - Notes and Reproductions of Art Work for Book on Ben Shahn, undated, (9 folders) (Box 6, Folder 33-41)
  - Notes Concerning Art Work, 1968, undated, (3 folders) (Box 6, Folder 42-44)
  - "Lists from Closet Walls," 1968, undated, (3 folders) (Box 7, Folder 1-3)
  - Minutes of Meetings, 1968-1999 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Notes Concerning Trees in Roosevelt, New Jersey, 1974-1985, (2 folders) (Box 7, Folder 5-6)
  - Notes Concerning Tokyo, Japan, 1980-1981 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Lists of Art Work from Retrospective Exhibition at Trenton City Museum, 1988 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Miscellaneous Notes about Ben Shahn by Bernarda Bryson Shahn, undated (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Miscellaneous Notes on 3.5-inch Floppy Discs, 1996-1997, undated, (6 folders) (Box 7, Folder 10-15)
  - Miscellaneous Notes, 1946-2001, undated, (7 folders) (Box 7, Folder 16-22)
  - Typescript "About Sidney," undated (Box 7, Folder 23)
  - Typescript "Alfred Dreyfus and Ben Shahn," undated (Box 7, Folder 24)
  - Typescript "Art and/or Consciousness," undated (Box 7, Folder 25)
  - Typescript "An Artistic Incident - The News Called It," undated (Box 7, Folder 26)
  - Typescript "Anecdotiques of Apollinaire,"undated (Box 7, Folder 27)
  - Typescript "Chaos," undated (Box 7, Folder 28)
  - Typescript for Novel Flight 112, undated (Box 7, Folder 29)
  - Typescript "The FSA File," undated (Box 7, Folder 30)
  - Manuscript for Play I and Self, undated (Box 7, Folder 31)
  - Typescript "Immortality of the Life of the Great Magician Cornelio Agrippa," undated (Box 7, Folder 32)
  - Typescript "Legend for the Cartoon," undated (Box 7, Folder 33)
  - Typescripts "A Letter to Many Friends" and "A Letter to My Italian Friends," undated (Box 7, Folder 34)
  - Typescripts for Short Story "Lunch Hour," undated, (3 folders) (Box 7, Folder 35-37)
  - Typescript "Notes in the Search for a Definition of Quality in Prints," undated (Box 7, Folder 38)
  - Typescript "Ode to Barbara," undated (Box 7, Folder 39)
  - Typescript "Of the Taller Archive of Ben Shahn's Works," undated (Box 7, Folder 40)
  - Typescript "Of the Wooden Mannequin," undated (Box 7, Folder 41)
  - Typescript "The Other Side of the Painting," undated (Box 7, Folder 42)
  - Typescript "Passage," undated (Box 7, Folder 43)
  - Typescript "Philosophy and/or Art," undated (Box 7, Folder 44)
  - Typescript "Possible Sequence of Ideas," undated (Box 7, Folder 45)
  - Typescript "The Problem of Artistic Creation in America Today," undated (Box 7, Folder 46)
  - Typescript "The Reel-Foot Lake Snake," undated (Box 7, Folder 47)
  - Typescript "The Skowhegan Idea," undated (Box 7, Folder 48)
  - Typescript "What Really Happened," undated (Box 7, Folder 49)
  - Typescript "The Wonderful World of Conjecture," undated (Box 7, Folder 50)
  - Typescripts for Untitled Stories, undated (Box 7, Folder 51)
  - Poems, undated (Box 7, Folder 52)
  - Typescript on Communism, 1948 (Box 7, Folder 53)
  - Typescripts on Japanese Printmaking, 1954-1959, (2 folders) (Box 7, Folder 54-55)
  - Typescript "Love and Joy about Letters," 1963 (Box 7, Folder 56)
  - Drafts for Book Ben Shahn's Drawings, undated, (20 folders) (Box 7, Folder 57-76)
  - Drafts for Book Ben Shahn's Drawings, undated, (24 folders) (Box 8, Folder 1-24)
  - Notes and Drafts for Book The Legend of Gilgamesh, (5 folders) (Box 8, Folder 25-29)
  - Draft for Book Images of Satan, undated, (7 folders) (Box 8, Folder 30-36)
  - Notes and Drafts for Book Twenty Miracles of Saint Nicholas, 1958, (10 folders) (Box 8, Folder 37-46)
  - Drafts for Book about Ben Shahn by Bernarda Bryson Shahn, 1972, (7 folders) (Box 8, Folder 47-53)
  - Typescript "Ben Shahn: Photographs and Paintings," 1985 (Box 8, Folder 54)
  - Typescript for Play The Epic of Gilgamesh, 1993 (Box 8, Folder 55)
  - Typescript for Speech, 1993 (Box 8, Folder 56)
  - Typescript "Third Allegory," 1994 (Box 8, Folder 57)
  - Notes and Drafts for "The Zoo of Zeus," 1997 (Box 8, Folder 58)
  - Miscellaneous Typescripts, undated (Box 8, Folder 59)
  - Typescript "Ben Shahn: Major American Artist" by Unidentified Author, undated (Box 8, Folder 60)
  - Typescript "Ben Shahn" by Unidentified Author, undated (Box 8, Folder 61)
  - Typescript "The White Gyrfalcon" by Charlton Ogburn, Jr., undated (Box 8, Folder 62)
  - Typescript about Ben Shahn "Self Arte," 1953 (Box 8, Folder 63)
  - Typescript by Carla Appel, 1998 (Box 8, Folder 64)
  - Typescript "Reconsidering the Hale County Record: Notes on Two Walker Evans Albums in the Library of Congress" by Beverly W. Brannan and Judith Keller, 1994 (Box 8, Folder 65)
  - Typescript "David Stone Martin" by Carmen Capalbo, undated (Box 8, Folder 66)
  - Typescript by Ruth Eisenstein, undated (Box 8, Folder 67)
  - Typescript "Pomegranada" by H. M. Koutoukas, undated (Box 8, Folder 68)
  - Poem by Edward Locke, undated (Box 8, Folder 69)
  - Poems by Gerald Metz, 1964, undated (Box 8, Folder 70)
  - Typescript "Ben Shahn, Mon Ami Tres Cher,?" by Fernand Mourlot, undated (Box 8, Folder 71)
  - Typescript by Norman Nadel, undated (Box 8, Folder 72)
  - Typescript "Ben Shahn's Mural in Roosevelt, N. J." by Sarah Peskin, 1970 (Box 8, Folder 73)
  - Typescript "Originality in Graphic Arts" by the Print Council of America, undated (Box 8, Folder 74)
  - Typescript of the Dreyfus Introduction, 1983 (Box 8, Folder 75)
  - Miscellaneous Typescripts by Warren Robbins, 1987-1993 (Box 8, Folder 76)
  - Typescript "Depression Years" by Edwin Rosskam, undated (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Typescript "Not Intended for Framing" by Edwin Rosskam, undated (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Typescript "Hildilid's Night" by Cheli Duran Ryan, undated (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Typescript "Ben Shahn" by J. T. S., undated (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Typescript "Ben Shahn and his Community" by Meredith Schor, 1992 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Notes by Ben Shahn for the Mural for the Rural Rehabilitation Program, undated (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Typescript "Imagination and Intention" possibly by Ben Shahn, undated (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Typescript "American Painting for the Past Twenty-Five Years" by Ben Shahn, 1951 (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Typescript for Talk "The Aspen Papers" by Ben Shahn, 1953 (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Handwritten Page by Ben Shahn, 1966 (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Typescript by Charles Westheimer, undated (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - Typescript "There's Power in the Brush" by Margareet Zoutewelle, 1996 (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - Miscellaneous Typescripts by Others, undated (Box 9, Folder 13)
- Diaries, 1965-1985, Series 4:; (Box 9; 5 folders)
  Bernarda Bryson Shahn 's diaries contain very brief daily entries and some illustrations. The 1972 diary contains much more elaborate illustrations.
  - Diary, 1965 (Box 9, Folder 14)
  - Diary, 1972 (Box 9, Folder 15)
  - Diary, 1973 (Box 9, Folder 16)
  - Diary, 1974 (Box 9, Folder 17)
  - Diary, 1985 (Box 9, Folder 18)